Guide to the Samuel Bowles Papers
Yale University Library
- Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts
  - Bowles discusses in this unascribed letter the position of the Phelps suit against the Republican [copy], 1856
    - Bowles points out to Sumner the cowards who deny theiraffiliationwith independence, as Alley. He hopes that they can all be together, or otherwise the reform movement must go outside the Republican Party. He says that Fenton will sell if he can get his price. He tells Sumner that he cannot escape his responsibility for coming out against Grant., 1872 Mar 30
    - Bowles writes Benjamin Gratz Brown that he will be in Cincinnati as a journalist only. He said that he had not in many years taken personal part in the parties. He believes that perhaps the Cincinnati nomination will fall on Adams., 1872 Apr 5
    - Bowles writes Richard Dudley Hubbard that he feels sorry for all of the bad things said about Hubbard, after receiving a letter from him. Bowles feels that he has refrained from too many of the good things. He tells Hubbard that he abandoned Connecticut when he saw it was going for Grant., 1872 Apr 5
    - Bowles discusses the presidential candidates other than Grant at Philadelphia or Greeley at Baltimore., 1872 May 11
    - Bowles tells Charles Sumner that the Republican, of course, had no authority in a matter of moral consciousness. Bird at Cincinnati has boasted that he defeated the Adams nomination. Bowles charges that this came straight from him. Bowles says that to him Sumner and Trumbull would have been an ideal ticket, and that Adams was above the Cincinnati movement., 1872 May 12
    - Bowles defends his believe in Greeley as a presidential candidate; he cannot comply with Olmstead's opinion of Greeley., 1872 May 15
    - Bowles writes Henry Laurens Dawes that he thinks Greeley has great possibilities in him for the coming election. He said that in several previous monthsWashingtonhad had the power to change things; now he believes that events will be in control., 1872 May 2
    - Bowles continues his own view of Greeley, but he admits that Olmstead's beliefs of Greeley as "humbug" contain some truth., 1872 May 21
    - Samuel Bowles writes Henry Laurens Dawes that he cannot say he has the courage to make the fight but will in his independent way. He says that he wanted Adams but accepted Greeley, since he is better than Grant. He wants to know what impression Bridgman had made upon Dawes., 1872 May 28
    - Bowles writes Carl Schurz that he wrote to Bullock and is not disappointed. He does not think Bullock's signature for the Cincinnati convention is necessary., 1872
    - Bowles tells Allen Thayer that in the distribution of the sheep and goats that he understands that Thayer is going with the goats., 1872
    - Bowles tells George Bliss that he seems to be spoiling for a fight with him. Bowles admits that perhaps the Republican misinterpreted the character of a Judge Blatchford; Bowles believes that his newspaper had an incomplete story. Bowles tells Bliss that the Republican has always avoided severe comments on Bliss. He says, on the contrary, that Bliss has made severe comments on the Republican., 1873 Jul 4
    - Bowles rebukes Russell for writing a "charming monograph" which had such a eulogistic style that he asked him where Achilles was., 1874 Jan 25
    - This letter from Bowles is unascribed. Bowles says that now he has letters of Josiah Clarkin hand. The request that Clark's letters be printed seems unreasonable to him. He will not publish it. [copy], 1874 Sep 2
    - Samuel Bowles writes Henry Alexander a letter requesting Alexander not to run for Congress because of his bad health. He tells him that he will have to oppose him politically if he does., 1874 Oct 19
    - Bowles writes John Wells that it is complimentary to be thought worthy of discipline by such as Wells. He thinks that he was not unjust to Phelps. Bowles thinks a wide field for judiciary reform is possible., 1875 Jun 18
    - Bowles answers Rieman on Mr. Reed by describing Reed as an honest, hard working preacher, but not an intellectual., 1876 Mar 25
    - Bowles writes C. B. Morrill that the making of a platform for Maine Democrats should wait until after the presidential nominations. He thinks it should at least wait until it is seen whether Blaine would make a contest for Morrill's place in the Senate., 1876 Jun 10
    - Bowles has a draft for a letter to Joseph H. Rieman recommending a Mr. Reid for a Presbyterian church., 1876
    - Bowles expresses a wish to see Carl Shurz. He discusses the conference and hopes it will be a success., 1876
    - Bowles writes George Washburn Smalley that there is nothing much new. He says that the Republican has made a commended place for itself. On the other hand, he believes that the Tribune has lost a great opportunity. Bowles says that the old distrust for Tilden is gone., 1876
    - Bowles tells Musgrave that he is not at all well, but he does hope to meet Halstead in New York. He tells Musgrave that if he is a man of peace, why did he slap poor Jennings' face., no date
    - Bowles write Alexander Turney Stewart and expresses disappointment that Cox was not made chairman of Ways and Means. He also discusses railroad disputes of the day., no date
    - Bowles tells Allen Thayer that he did not mean to seem contemptuous. Bowles said that he did not think that Thayer was pledged to Adams, but he did think that he was absolutely independent. Afterwards, Bowles had strong evidence that Thayer was working for Rice., no date
    - Anna Callender Brackett, educator, has had a poem published in Harper's. She wonders if Bowles will make some copies for her., 1877 Feb 20
    - Anna Callender Brackett writes a thank you to Bowles for publishing a poem of hers; she also gives a description of a recent trip., 1877 Sep 2
    - Lizzia Branciard wants to know if Bowles knows of anyone who would need a correspondent such as she to attend the Paris Exposition., 1877 Sep 1
    - H. O. Bristadt thanks Bowles for a copy of the Republican., 1875 May 5
    - Benjamin Gratz Brown tells Bowles that he had read a telegram and could see that Bowles would be with them in Cincinnati., 1876 Mar 30
    - Chamberlain thanks Bowles for his kindness expressed in the Republican. He tells Bowles that he has been able to see some reasons for doubt., 1875 Mar 30
    - Chamberlain writes Bowles that he hopes Grant will declare himself on their side. He says that sight could not be lost of the fact that they are Southern not Northern Republicans. He expressed admiration for Bowles' independent course., 1876 Feb 2
    - Chester Williams Chapin gives an expression of the dull time of politics and an unenthusiastic reception of the Cincinnati candidate., 1876 Jun 20
    - Josiah Clark writes George Merriam a letter which identifies Merriam as the author of an article called "Candor." The article concerns the Beecher trial. Clark condemned the Republican as being "gossipy.", 1874 Aug 28
    - Mary Clemmer writes Bowles thanking him for his kind friendship and for a photograph book., 1862 Mar 24
    - Phoebe W. Couzins writes Bowles remembering a very pleasant visit by him in St. Louis. Bowles has said he will mention items of her "pen and tongue." She sends him a copy of "Ballot Box," published in Toledo on behalf of women., 1876 Aug 16
    - Isaac Curry of Richmond, Virginia, calls Bowles' attention to an article he has written on "Executive Patronage of Civil Service.", 1877 May 17
    - Richard Henry Dana, Jr., tells Bowles that he has dealt exactly right with the delicate subject of legal tenders., 1874 Apr 20
    - Richard Henry Dana, Jr., is overwhelmed with congratulations on a stand which the Republican took on a law suit., 1875 May 6
    - Richard Henry Dana, Jr., tells Bowles why he did not vote for Greeley., 1876 Mar 16
    - Richard Henry Dana, Jr., asks Bowles to reprint an article., 1876 Mar 20
    - Sam Davis tells Bowles of his bouts with rheumatism and briefly discusses David Ames Wells., no date
    - Henry Laurens Dawes is giving Bowles his views onprohibitorylaw. He thinks the law is a gross mistake., 1855 Oct 2
    - Henry Laurens Dawes is enjoying a vacation and apologizes for not having seen Bowles in so long. Dawes has seen the Blaine correspondence and is surprised at Blaine's denial of the problem of the Speakership Contest. He says in that case half of the House must be liars., 1869 Apr 18
    - Henry Laurens Dawes writes to Bowles, pondering on reasons that he has not heard from Bowles in so long. He tells Bowles that he knows he was dissatisfied with the way the convention went. He thinks that Bowles is wrong about Fenton, for he believes Fenton was for Greeley all along., 1872 May 19
    - Dawes discusses the Wool and Woolens Tariff of 1868 and commends Bowles on his philosophy in politics., 1872 May 26
    - Dawes congratulates Mr. and Mrs. Bowles on their twenty-fifth wedding anniversary., 1873 Sep 6
    - Dawes discusses a speech of his own about which he has received many letters; he congratulates Bowles on his ability to make "glorious fights.", 1873 Dec 15
    - Dawes is discouraged with the Republican Party and compares the present administration with the Gladstone Ministry in England; he believes that the Republican Party can be saved by the "folly of its opponents.", 1874 Feb 6
    - Dawes tells Bowles that he is one of the few people who think of him now except in connection with the tariff., 1874 Feb 8
    - Dawes thanks Bowles for his support against the Sanborn Contracts., 1874 Mar 2
    - Dawes again speaks of an affair with John D. Sanborn and talks also of a man named Sam Hooker., 1874 Mar 5
    - Dawes is especially unhappy as he writes this letter to Bowles. He feels that he is called "weak" when he has to make certain decisions. Dawes fears that he and Bowles are drawn apart: Bowles by journalistic apostates and Dawes by political friends., 1874 Oct 15
    - Dawes discusses his own future in politics: a. He thinks that he will not be needed after the state is saved. b. He wonders why the Republicans have elected Pierce, Harris, Stevens, and Talbot. c. He asks Bowles to deal with George D. Robinson, and he will deal with John Randolph Tucker of Virginia., 1874 Oct 17
    - Dawes writes Bowles that affairs in Washington are especially bad. He says that the Currency Bill was forced through without the chance of an amendment. He thinks that Phil Sheridan always blunders., 1875 Jan 7
    - Dawes thanks Bowles for a good article about him in the Republican. He says that he tries to love his enemies, but the fellows in the West make it difficult., 1875 Jan 23
    - Dawes says that Bowles' idea of the Congressional situation is purely as an outsider., 1875 Feb 2
    - Dawes is ashamed of the conditions in Washington at this time; he is afraid it is the death of the Republican Party., 1876 Mar 5
    - Dawes writes of Benjamin F. Butler, saying he is a man who likes to see things smashed up generally., 1876 Mar 26
    - Dawes discusses Richard Henry Dana, Jr., as a man who doesn't have much common sense., 1876 Apr 2
    - Dawes explains to Bowles that he cannot interfere with the election of delegates from Massachusetts., 1876 May 18
    - Dawes speaks of a certain amount of "dirty work" done by Newton Booth of California, as well as his influence with Tilden., 1877 Feb 17
    - Dawes briefly mentions Frelinghuysen. He cites the fall of Adam and the landing of the Pilgrims as the two greatest calamities that ever befell man., n.y. Mar 23
    - Walker accuses a man named Traps of being a cabinet maker and anupholsterer, as related by Dawes. Dawes discusses the controversy between himself and James G. Blaine regarding the House Speakership Contest of 1869., no date
    - M. D. Defrees discusses with Bowles the presidential possibilities of 1876., 1876 May 18
    - Defrees discusses the possible Republican and Democratic candidates with Bowles. He thinks that the Republicans will nominate either Blaine of Conkling., 1876 May 24
    - Defrees thanks Bowles for some Republican articles. He tells Bowles that he is wrong about the position of a Morrison., 1876 Jun 4
    - Defrees says that the name of Judge Davis cannot be presented at the St. Louis convention with his consent., 1876 Jun 21
    - Anna E. Dickinson congratulates Bowles on being a "good" hater. She discusses the possibility of going to England and hopes Bowles will write her there., 1871 Apr 7
    - Anna E. Dickinson sent a pamphlet to Bowles to be published in Springfield., 1877 Jan 26
    - Matthew Paul Drady expresses to Bowles preference for Adams in the forthcoming election. He says his Republican convention had expressed some preference for Blaine., 1876 May 10
    - Matthew Paul Drady tells Bowles of a commencement address which he made at Wallamet University., 1876 Aug 11
    - Matthew Paul Drady thanks Bowles for his kind remarks to the graduating class of Salem. He comments on Hayes as doing pretty well considering the atmosphere. He says that Sherman is a machine man in the cabinet., 1877 Aug 10
    - Duclay writes Murat Halstead that force was not used in a Mississippi problem. He says that Bowles wants Charles Francis Adams, Jr., not Mr. Halstead., 1875 Nov 30
    - William Greenleaf Eliot sends Bowles a copy of an inaugural address of Washington University, St. Louis. He feels the need for a university in the West and would like to appeal for Boston wealth., 1872 May 11
    - William Maxwell Evarts acknowledges a note from Bowles and apologizes for being unable to make a proposed speech., no date
    - David Dudley Field acknowledges a letter received from Bowles and wishes him better luck next time for a cause., 1871 Aug 3
    - Henry Martyn Field, editor of the N.Y. Evangelist,, had published conspicuously some material for Bowles., 1874 Dec 3
    - Forbes writes Bowles that he is correct in setting Dawes right in a false position. He wishes that Dawes would defend himself in a position sadly misunderstood., 1871 Mar 11
    - Forbes discusses Butler with Bowles whom he believes is not so smart as he should be., 1871 Mar 14
    - Forbes hopes Bowles will call attention to a Mr. Pope in the Republican., 1873 Nov 24
    - John Murray Forbes writes Bowles that Judge Hoar has not the faculty of conciliating men., 1874 Apr 23
    - Gardner informs Bowles that he is not thin-skinned., 1855 Apr 18
    - Gardner acknowledges Bowles' note and says that he values the praise of the legislature very highly. He tells Bowles that the modified personal liberty bill was never printed., 1855 May 23
    - Henry Joseph Gardner seconds a commission to Bowles as payment of his respect. He has had a letter from Governor Johnson saying he had not received his due. He wants Bowles to send him a Republican copy to give him a "puff.", 1855 Jun 26
    - Gardner says he was sorry not to see Bowles on a certain day. He tells of his loyalties at a Philadelphia convention to General Wilson. Gardner feels there are those who want him out of office and wants Bowles' feelings on it., 1855 Aug 17
    - Gardner tells Bowles that he has no patience with him on his tortuous course against him., 1855 Sep 17
    - Gardner points out that there was a Republican article that was very vindictive towards him., 1855
    - Gardner points out that he has received no letter from Bowles., 1855
    - Gardner thanks Bowles for a letter, but he tells him that he will have to be more specific about "recognized friends.", 1855
    - Gardner discusses a question raised by some gentlemen from New York. He questions whether members of the council should be bound by a majority. This letter is unascribed., no date
    - James A. Garfield writes David Ames Wells and thanks him for the perusal of a Bowles' letter. He says that Bowles is mistaken in his association with Blaine - that he has wanted no one to ask favors for him. Garfield states that actually he would like a free lance in the House rather than running a committee. He says that he is disgusted with politics., 1873 Nov 14
    - Washington Gladden discussed with Bowles the criticism of Henry Chandler Bowen, ad manager of the Independent., 1871 Jan 27
    - L. N. Goodell thanks Bowles for sending him certain information. The letter contains a discussion of a Mr. Gustafson who is discussed as being affable when he likes., 1877 Jun 27
    - Lessie Goodell Gustafson writes Bowles to discoverwhathe can of Alexis Gustafson, a deserter from the U.S. Signal Service., 1877 Jun 24
    - Richard B. Gwin compliments Bowles on a good article in the Republican. He is especially impressed with Bowles' insistence on honor., 1874 Dec 26
    - Richard B. Gwin says that it is worth writing to Bowles when we get such good response. He says he hopes never to meet Dawes again., n.y. Dec 30
    - Susan Hab relates to Bowles that she has written to Caroline Briggs about the matter of the Old South and relates this to Bowles., 1877 Jan 27
    - E. B. Haskell wonders if Bowles can help him by any letter to the inside of the newspaper business in London or Paris., 1872 Jun 11
    - E. B. Haskell said that he spent three days in Washington at Bowles' suggestion. He had an interview with Sumner and interesting talks with various Washington dignitaries., 1874 Mar 12
    - Joseph Roswell Hawley tells Bowles that he was in Washington when he received his letter, or he would have answered it sooner. He says that he would like to be senator., 1871 Oct 25
    - Joseph Roswell Hawley said he has never seen so many lies as Senator Smith has told about the U.S. Centennial Commission., 1874 Feb 4
    - Joseph Roswell Hawley writes to Bowles for advice on the fact that the Connecticut delegation has decided to nominate Marshall Jewell for president., 1876 Apr 24
    - Joseph Roswell Hawley has read in the Republican of the foolishness and meanness of the Republican in assailing Landers for non-attendance at sessions of Congress. He tells Bowles that Landers answered 8 roll calls out of about 106. He points out to Bowles that Landers is only noted as a dodger., n.y. Oct 24
    - Rutherford Birchard Hayes encloses a paragraph from the Republican in his letter, which holds Hayes responsible for appointing George H. Butler to special post office agency in the Black Hills. Hayes replies to Bowles that the paragraph was a total mistake. He says that he never heard of the position until Butler was appointed. He tells Bowles that "placating" was not his way and that he only tried to do what was right., 1877 Jun 7
    - Thomas Wentworth Higginson has just read a budget of notices from a book sent by a Mr. Pitman. He said that the notices were cruel and tells Bowles that he should change the name of Across the Continent to A Voyage Around the World. World., 1875 Jun 19
    - Roswell Dwight Hitchcock thanks Bowles for a copy of the Republican., no date
    - Josiah Gilbert Holland discusses with Bowles the purchase of stock in the Republican and his respect for the friendship of Samuel Bowles., 1860 Apr 2
    - Josiah Gilbert Holland sends Bowles condolences on the death of his brother, Ben., 1876 Feb 6
    - Isabella Beecher Hooker writes Bowles asking him to tell her his views on Britain before going home., 1862 Apr 29
    - Isabella Hooker proposes a necessary meeting between the Bowles and the Hookers in Hartford or Springfield., 1876 Jan 5
    - Isabella Beecher Hooker writes to Bowles concerning Connecticut on woman suffrage. She discusses a bill drawn up by her husband, Richard, on suffrage and a speech which she made in the State Senate., 1877 Mar 26
    - Isabella Hooker writes Bowles that she has now found the proceedings of the Woman's Rights Convention held at Seneca Falls, New York, July, 1848., 1877 Mar 26
    - Alice S. Hooper writes a letter to Bowles with an enclosure (which was not in the letter) and discusses the enclosure in congruency with a policy of Great Britain., 1877 Jan 7
    - Julia Ward Howe writes Bowles a note on justice for the dead., 1874 Mar 7
    - Hubbard thanks Bowles for his very generous treatment of him and states that if he is defeated in the election the Republican will be largely responsible., 1872 Apr 1
    - Hubbard congratulates Bowles on the choice of Dana as counsel. He praises Bowles on his discriminating criticism; yet he thinks politics are corrupt and does not understand how Charles Sumner could have remained upright., 1874 Apr 19
    - Richard Dudley Hubbard congratulates Bowles on a law suit, telling him he would have been victorious except for a small technicality., 1875 May 6
    - Edmund Hudson writes Bowles that he understands that the Republican has information that George H. Butler was not appointed by the cabinet. Hudson says his information came from a member of the cabinet. Hudson says that Talbot of Maine has been replaced. He has talked to Sherman about the latter; he says that Talbot was one of the few Maine Republicans who had not bowed his knee to Blaine. He related that Bret Harte was in Georgetown, poverty stricken., 1877 Jun 12
    - Frederick Dan Huntington writes Bowles an article to be reprinted in the Republican., 1876 Sep 7
    - Huntington writes that he appreciated Bowles' approval of his work at Emmanuel Church, Boston, and as deacon of Trinity Church., 1860 Feb 6
    - W. H. Huntington writes to Bowles of Smalley and personal relations., 1872 Apr 28
    - W. H. Huntington writes to a Mr. Wells. He says that he came across in reading an instance on paper currency. He sends it along with thanks for a new copy of Robinson Crusoe., 1876 Aug
    - Marietta Hutchinson writes Bowles a note of congratulations on his daughter's marriage. She says she has lost contact with many old friends and hopes to see the Bowles again., 1874 Jul 5
    - F. B. Jackson expresses regret at the death of Bowles' brother., 1876 Aug 9
    - Helen Hunt Jackson asks Bowles to come to Colorado., 1874 Apr 26
    - Helen Hunt Jackson writes Bowles that they are now at their home in Princeton and again asks Bowles to come visit., 1876 Aug 18
    - Helen Hunt Jackson writes an apology to Bowles that they will not be able to meet Bowles due to a complication of plans., 1876 Oct 8
    - Helen Hunt Jackson writes Mrs. Bowles, asking the Bowles to come visit them in Colorado Springs., 1877 Apr 26
    - William Sharpless Jackson sends a note of apology to Bowles for not having answered a query. He wants Bowles to come to Colorado for a volley around June 1. Helen Hunt Jackson adds a postscript on her husband's masculine way of putting things., 1876 Feb 27
    - Jewell tells Bowles of various places he will be traveling. He invites Bowles to eat with him in the Massasoit., 1876 Mar 25
    - Jewell confirms an engagement to meet Bowles and tells Bowles to invite the kind of people he likes., 1876 Mar 30
    - Jewell said he has told the Post to dry up. He points out that Booth said a good thing about Blaine. He says he had a nice letter from Schurz., 1877 Mar 21
    - Jewell invites Bowles to come and dine., 1877 Jul 11
    - Jewell says that Friday will be a good day, and he will be at home. He tells Bowles that he will meet him at the train., 1877 Jul 13
    - Oliver Johnson tells Bowles that he cannot understand what he had done that would cause him to be stigmatized as an infidel by the Republican. He says that the name Christian has covered all the radicalism he knows., 1875 Nov 16
    - Johnson writes Bowles that he understands that Bowles did not mean to call him an infidel but that the vast number of orthodox people would takeit inthe extreme. He also wants to know if there is a good country journal of which he can have control., 1875 Nov 18
    - Oliver Johnson wants to know why the Republican lends its columns to such unscrupulous papers as the Brooklyn Review and the New York Sun., 1876 Jan 22